<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Leo&#39;s Long Covid Blog</title>
<link>https://leonidliu.github.io/long_covid_blog/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://leonidliu.github.io/long_covid_blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>A blog chronicling Leo&#39;s journey with Long Covid, with a dash of data</description>
<generator>quarto-1.2.269</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 May 2023 04:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>One-Year Covid Anniversary Gratitude</title>
  <dc:creator>Leo Liu</dc:creator>
  <link>https://leonidliu.github.io/long_covid_blog/posts/one-year-gratitude/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Today marks the one-year anniversary of my first-and-only Covid infection. (Knock on wood.)</p>
<p>365 days ago, I woke up with a fever. Within an hour, there it was. The aggressive red line I’d only ever seen in pictures, so thick it left no doubt whether it was Covid or not. Dispiriting as that was, after successfully avoiding infection for two years, it wouldn’t be until about a month later that I’d start to see just how much my life was about to change.</p>
<p>365 days later, I wish I could say, <em>I’m fully recovered</em>. But I can’t. The perhaps-luckiest long haulers do heal completely within their first year. And although I am nonetheless lucky on the full spectrum of Long Covid, I’m still somewhere in the vast and amorphous space in between <em>sick</em> and <em>better</em> that most young people never consider.</p>
<p>Recovery status aside — I am far enough into Covid recovery to know it’s already changed me forever, and not entirely for the worse!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://leonidliu.github.io/long_covid_blog/posts/one-year-gratitude/hammock.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="An Asian man smiling, wearing a mask, and in a hammock under his desk" width="500"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">A picture of me, masked, in a hammock under my desk</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I am choosing to mark my one-year milestone with a gratitude list. For the things I could’ve lost this year, but didn’t. For the things that changed, maybe in some ways for the better. For the things I even gained along the way.</p>
<section id="on-this-day-im-grateful-for" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="on-this-day-im-grateful-for">On this day, I’m grateful for …</h2>
<p><strong>My body.</strong> I used to push my body so hard, as a result of extroversion, work, exercise, travel, and more. This year, I learned the importance of listening to and supporting my body as best I can. I nearly lost all of my health and quality of life this year, and this is the only body I’ll ever have. I honor and give thanks to my body’s resilience, for carrying me this far, and for continuing to heal through the biggest physical trauma it’s encountered in three decades.</p>
<p><strong>My care team.</strong> This includes my physical therapist, my psychotherapist, my osteopath, my integrative medicine doctor, my cardiologist, my neurologist, my primary care physician, my lymphatic drainage masseuse, and others I’ve seen too. It took months to assemble the medical team I needed — a unique mix of qualities I value including direct lived experience with Long Covid, willingness to try unconventional treatments, availability and responsiveness, and openness to engaging back and forth as our collective scientific understanding of Long Covid evolves.</p>
<p><strong>Family, chosen family, and friends.</strong> I really don’t know where I’d be without these people. They’re some of the most loving, generous, and unwavering people I’ve ever met. My mother, her partner, and my brother flew out from Southern California to DC to visit me and help take care of me. Members of my chosen family in DC and beyond have rotated to provide me at-home care, rides to medical appointments, drug and food drop-offs, and endless emotional support. Friends near and far have checked-in, offered companionship over Zoom, sent me delivered meals, and more. I am forever indebted to and grateful for each person who has shown up for me. It’s because of the care I’ve received from my people this year that I now understand what true love and interdependence look like.</p>
<p><strong>Fellow long haulers and chronically-ill folks.</strong> How lonely this year would’ve been without the support of people who <em>really</em> get it. Who understand symptom flares, “crashes,” medical dismissal, and endless grief. Who understand the pain of being left behind by politicians, economists, and even people we think of as friends — at a time when <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/society/2023/may/27/immunologist-akiko-iwasaki-we-are-not-done-with-covid-not-even-close?CMP=share_btn_tw">we’re not done with Covid, not even close.</a> This includes online groups like <a href="https://www.wearebodypolitic.com/">Body Politic</a>, Long Covid Community, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/covidlonghaulers/">r/covidlonghaulers</a>; as well as individual people who I’ve met in-person or online. I have so many Long Covid and chronically-ill buddies now, and I am grateful for each one.</p>
<p><strong>Long Covid and other post-viral illness researchers.</strong> Like <a href="https://twitter.com/VirusesImmunity">Akiko Iwasaki</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/PutrinoLab">David Putrino</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/resiapretorius">Resia Pretorius</a>, and Brian Walitt, who are investigating the causes, characteristics, mechanisms, and potential treatments of all of the diseases that may lie within the umbrellas of Long Covid, ME/CFS, POTS, and associated conditions. Of course, I also can’t forget the patient-led research efforts and researchers, such as the <a href="https://patientresearchcovid19.com/">Patient-Led Research Collaborative</a>, <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41579-022-00846-2">Hannah Davis</a>, <a href="https://osf.io/n9e75/">Lisa McCorkell</a>, and <a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/eclinm/article/PIIS2589-5370(21)00299-6/fulltext#%20">Gina Assaf</a>. I’m grateful for the daily work of these researchers, whose work literally generates hope and the possibility of a better future for people like me.</p>
<p><strong>Public health communicators.</strong> <a href="https://erictopol.substack.com/">Eric Topol</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/luckytran">Lucky Tran</a>, <a href="https://peoplescdc.org/">People’s CDC</a>, and more. These people and groups have done an incredible job accessibly communicating through the various stages of the ongoing Covid crisis — not just translating up-to-date public health data in a way that the public can understand, but doing so in a way that really considers the protection of high-risk and the most-impacted people as an ongoing priority of public health policy and behavior.</p>
<p><strong>Disability justice activists.</strong> Such as my dear friend <a href="https://leavingevidence.wordpress.com/">Mia Mingus</a>, as well as others like <a href="https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/688504/year-of-the-tiger-by-alice-wong/">Alice Wong</a> and <a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/the-future-is-disabled-prophecies-love-notes-and-mourning-songs-leah-lakshmi-piepzna-samarasinha/18247280?ean=9781551528915">Leah Lakshmi Piepzna-Samarasinha</a>. Disability justice activists continue to teach me that long before Long Covid, disabled people for centuries and millennia have experienced what I am experiencing today. And the most recent cohort of newly-disabled people have a lot to be appreciative about for the existence of frameworks like disability justice to orient us toward the world <em>as it could be</em>. A world in which community care, interdependence, and access intimacy trump the status quo of capitalism, able-bodied convenience, and the appearance of “normal.”</p>
<p><strong>And, of course, my readers.</strong> I appreciate your witnessing of my journey. I appreciate every message I’ve received, every time my blog has been shared with someone else, and the serendipitous connections my readers make me aware of. I hope that my words can help some of you who may be struggling with Long Covid or similar conditions as mine.</p>
<p>Because of this list, my heart is full today. To my body, to my people, to my readers, and to all those who choose to stand with us long haulers every single day — thank you.</p>
</section>
<section id="up-next" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="up-next">Up next</h2>
<p>It’s been awhile since I’ve posted. There’s a lot of ground I didn’t get to cover, in these past few months, that I’d like to write about. For example, I got <strong>microclot</strong> imaging done, which may shed light on my condition. I have hundreds of data points from my six-day research trial at the National Institute of Health. And finally, I still would like to update my readers around my POTS and my gut microbiome, subjects which I introduced <a href="https://leonidliu.github.io/long_covid_blog/posts/pots-1/">here</a> and <a href="https://leonidliu.github.io/long_covid_blog/posts/gut-1/">here</a>.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <guid>https://leonidliu.github.io/long_covid_blog/posts/one-year-gratitude/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 30 May 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://leonidliu.github.io/long_covid_blog/posts/one-year-gratitude/hammock.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Gut Update: ‘The Dysbiosis Hypothesis’</title>
  <dc:creator>Leo Liu</dc:creator>
  <link>https://leonidliu.github.io/long_covid_blog/posts/gut-1/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>When I got infected with Covid this May, I told myself, <em>I probably won’t get Long Covid.</em></p>
<p>At that point in the pandemic, Long Covid <em>was</em> what I was afraid of. After all, as a generally-healthy, triple-vaccinated person, I didn’t have to be too worried about severe acute illness or death. It was the <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/pressroom/nchs_press_releases/2022/20220622.htm">one in five</a> chance of not recovering — and the possibility of becoming <a href="https://www.hhs.gov/civil-rights/for-providers/civil-rights-covid19/guidance-long-covid-disability/index.html">disabled</a> — that scared me.</p>
<p>But I reassured myself that at least I was lucky to not have known risk factors: I wasn’t <a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/eclinm/article/PIIS2589-5370(22)00354-6/fulltext">unvaccinated</a>, <a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/fullarticle/2797443?guestAccessKey=07377a3e-8fa8-4f8e-b336-381e6899b698&amp;utm_source=For_The_Media&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=ftm_links&amp;utm_content=tfl&amp;utm_term=101022">female</a>, or <a href="https://www.cell.com/cell/fulltext/S0092-8674(22)00072-1">diabetic</a>. In my teenage years, I had avoided contracting a virus like the one that causes mono, which Covid <a href="https://www.cell.com/cell/fulltext/S0092-8674(22)00072-1?_returnURL=https%3A%2F%2Flinkinghub.elsevier.com%2Fretrieve%2Fpii%2FS0092867422000721%3Fshowall%3Dtrue">can reactivate</a> even years later.</p>
<p>Not only that, I probably got a reduced viral load due to wearing my <strong>KN95</strong> mask, and I managed to get access to a full course of the antiviral medication <strong>Paxlovid</strong>, which current research says slightly <a href="https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.11.03.22281783v1">reduces</a> the chance of Long Covid.</p>
<p>But months later, here I am, sick <em>and</em> disabled with the very condition I tried so hard to avoid.</p>
<p>Herein lies a puzzle: was it pure bad luck? Or was there <em>something</em> about my otherwise-good health that could’ve contributed to my developing a debilitating medical condition? This is an important question — not as a matter of self-blame, but because I know firsthand that the Covid pandemic is not over, no matter what <a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/09/19/1123767437/joe-biden-covid-19-pandemic-over">President Biden has said</a>. As long as I can get reinfected, my Long Covid could get <a href="https://www.longcovidkids.org/post/a-world-first-effect-of-covid-reinfection-on-people-living-with-long-covid">worse</a>, or I could recover and get it again.</p>
<section id="enter-the-dysbiosis-hypothesis" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="enter-the-dysbiosis-hypothesis">Enter, the Dysbiosis Hypothesis</h2>
<p>I may never know exactly why I got Long Covid, but I’ve read enough science to have a hypothesis. It has to do with my gut microbiome.</p>
<p>Today, researchers know that the <strong>gut microbiome</strong> — the collection of trillions of microbes and bacteria living inside of the human gut — plays a major role in our overall health and well-being. An estimated 70-80% of the human immune system is located in the gut. And beyond the immune system, it also influences <a href="https://sonnenburglab.stanford.edu/press.html">countless</a> other aspects of our health, such as our mood, nervous system, and weight.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://leonidliu.github.io/long_covid_blog/posts/gut-1/gut-microbiome.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="An illustration of the beneficial bacteria in the gut" width="409"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">“<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/132318516@N08/29872812646">Beneficial Gut Bacteria</a>” by National Institutes of Health (NIH) is licensed under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/?ref=openverse">CC BY-NC 2.0</a>.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Studies have shown that patients with Long Covid are <a href="https://www.nih.gov/news-events/nih-research-matters/covid-19-disrupts-gut-microbiome">much more likely</a> to have <strong>dysbiosis</strong>, a disrupted and out-of-balance gut microbiome, than patients who have recovered from Covid more quickly. For instance, <a href="https://gut.bmj.com/content/71/3/544">one study</a> found that Long Covid patients specifically tend to have less concentration of <em>Bifidobacterium pseudocatenulatum</em> and <em>Faecalibacterium prausnitzii</em>, beneficial bacteria species linked to better immunity.</p>
<p>In the nine months before my infection, I unfortunately had to take several rounds of antibiotics. Five, in fact: two for tonsillitis, one for strep throat, one for gonorrhea, and one after I was so tired of tonsil problems that I got them removed. With so much antibiotic usage in so short a period of time, it’d be surprising if my gut microbiome <em>wasn’t</em> out of balance. Sadly, I didn’t have too much of a choice. Antibiotics are prescribed so often because they work.</p>
<p>In short, my dysbiosis hypothesis is this: my gut microbiome hadn’t yet healed from several rounds of antibiotics, and Long Covid resulted from the virus taking advantage of my temporarily vulnerable gut. Taken further, the virus might even have found a way to take up residence in the relatively hospitable environment that is the gut. The virus and viral fragments have been found <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC9057012/">within the gut tissue</a> of infected people, which is one reason why viral persistence has become a prevailing theory of why some people suffer from Long Covid.</p>
</section>
<section id="data" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data">Data</h2>
<p>Suspecting dysbiosis, I ordered a commercial microbiome test from the company <a href="https://www.ombrelab.com/">Ombre</a> to better understand the health of my gut microbiome.</p>
<p>The test cost $100 and was surprisingly easy to self-administer. Describing the process would be more graphic than I care to do online, but let’s just say it involved a swab, a test tube, and used toilet paper. I sent in my sample and got my results back within two weeks.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://leonidliu.github.io/long_covid_blog/posts/gut-1/gut-test-results-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="An image depicting levels of various beneficial bacteria" width="586"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Results from my microbiome test; analysis by <a href="https://www.biomesight.com/">Biomesight</a>. Sep 2022.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Shown above are estimated concentrations of my <em>good</em> bacterial genera from my sample. Of seven measured genera, the free-of-cost analysis by Biomesight categorized me as “low” on six. Two in particular — <em>Akkermansia</em> (which plays a role in strengthening the gut lining to prevent leakage) and <em>Bifidobacterium</em> (which plays a role in modulating the body’s immune responses) — appeared nonexistent or nearly so, at estimated concentrations of 0.000% and 0.002% respectively.</p>
<p><em>Yikes!</em></p>
<p>How about the two beneficial strains in the <a href="https://gut.bmj.com/content/71/3/544">aforementioned</a> study on patients with Long Covid? Well, <em>Faecalibacterium prausnitzii</em> was detected at the low concentration of 2.879% and <em>Bifidobacterium pseudocatenulatum</em> was not detected at all.</p>
<p><em>Double yikes!</em></p>
<p>Not shown are the concentrations of my <em>bad</em> bacterial genera, mostly because they also appeared low. That was good news, at least.</p>
<p>Now, I don’t know how accurate these commercial tests are, or what research may back the presented interval ranges, but between my antibiotic history and these results, it feels safe to say that I am currently experiencing some form of dysbiosis. With low levels of important beneficial bacteria, I’d guess that my gut is (still) vulnerable to opportunistic infections. Rebuilding these populations seems to me a no-brainer in my journey to restored health — and perhaps even toward full recovery.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-im-trying" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-im-trying">What I’m trying</h2>
<p>Many (but not all) of the interventions below are suggested by the pioneering research of Stanford microbiologists Erica and Justin Sonnenburg. They detail some of them in their published book, <em>The Good Gut</em>, and another is suggested by a <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34256014/">recent study</a> they collaborated on showing durable benefits to the microbiome as a result of increased fermented food intake.</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Eating several servings of fermented food every day.</strong> For me, this includes a daily glass of homemade kefir, a fermented milk drink similar to yogurt, as well more kimchi, sauerkraut, and miso in general.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Eating a wider range of fruits and vegetables, and eating less red meat.</strong> Especially foods that are vibrant and colorful.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Supplementing with probiotics and prebiotics.</strong> For example, Garden of Life has several formulations of <strong>probiotics</strong> (live good bacteria) containing high <em>Bifido</em> counts, as well as <strong>prebiotics</strong> (which help good bacterial populations thrive).</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Spending time in nature and with dogs, when I can.</strong> Both are good ways to expose myself to healthy bacteria, and good for my mental health, too. Since I live in DC, this sometimes means dogs and Rock Creek Park!</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Drinking more bone broth.</strong> Not mentioned by the Sonnenbergs, but is nonetheless supposedly helpful for repairing the lining of the gut.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Outside of my early Paxlovid course, I haven’t tried any antivirals that might combat viral persistence, should viral persistence explain my condition, though perhaps I will in the future.</p>
<p>In the future, I may also see if an integrative medicine doctor can offer me more targeted guidance.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-its-going" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-its-going">How it’s going</h2>
<p>I’ve made these changes to my diet for roughly three months, now. And so far, so good!</p>
<p>My appreciation for fermented foods has definitely grown. I’m craving the tangy flavor of fermented food more than ever before. I especially think my life has been improved by the addition of homemade kefir, which I tell my friends is “the champagne of milk” for it’s fun, luscious fizziness.</p>
<p>As for the cheapest way to assess my gut health from week to week, you’ll just have to trust me when I say that my stool frequency and consistency have improved, too. Google “Bristol Stool Chart,” if you’re interested in more on that. It’s a real medical tool.</p>
<p>Beyond that, I plan to retake the Ombre test in another month or two for comparison.</p>
</section>
<section id="disclaimer" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="disclaimer">Disclaimer</h2>
<p>I’m not a medical professional. Before introducing fermented food or probiotics into your diet, you might consider consulting with an experienced doctor. For example, fermented food is high in histamine, which some people with Long Covid cannot tolerate. And caution with probiotics could be warranted for those who are immunocompromised or taking immunosuppresants.</p>
<p>Also, I have no affiliation with Ombre or Biomesight.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <category>gut</category>
  <guid>https://leonidliu.github.io/long_covid_blog/posts/gut-1/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2022 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://leonidliu.github.io/long_covid_blog/posts/gut-1/gut-microbiome.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>POTS Update: ‘The scooter incident’</title>
  <dc:creator>Leo Liu</dc:creator>
  <link>https://leonidliu.github.io/long_covid_blog/posts/pots-1/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>It wasn’t until about three months into my Long Covid that I began to have trouble with my heart rate.</p>
<p>I was having a good month by the standards of my new medical condition, so I took the opportunity to try to squeeze in a haircut. I was still trying to be careful — not wanting another episode of <strong>post-exertional malaise (PEM)</strong>, a subject for a future blog post — so I took an electric scooter to and from the barbershop, fifteen minutes away.</p>
<p>I thought my body could handle an electric scooter ride. After all, at this point in my recovery, I was doing a daily 15-20 minute walk, albeit with a break every five minutes. And I’d taken shorter scooter trips a few times without incident.</p>
<p>But partway through the trip, I noticed on my FitBit that my heart rate had shot up to 130 beats per minute. A full 60 higher than my resting heart rate of 70. As far as I could tell, just from standing and balancing on the electric scooter on a warm day.</p>
<p><em>Uh oh, that’s not normal.</em></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://leonidliu.github.io/long_covid_blog/posts/pots-1/scooter.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A set of black electric scooters with pink design, strewn on the ground" width="464"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">A picture of electric scooters on the ground by <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/quintanomedia/">quintanomedia</a>, licensed under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">CC BY 2.0</a></figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>At the barbershop, I noticed malaise setting in as my haircut proceeded. The feeling of being sick and mildly poisoned crept down my head and neck. With the barber making small talk, my ability to hold conversation quickly diminished.</p>
<section id="fast-forward-nearly-two-months-later" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="fast-forward-nearly-two-months-later">Fast forward, nearly two months later</h2>
<p>Seemingly starting with the scooter incident, elevated heart rate has now become a way of life. Rarely does five minutes of being upright pass without me checking the heart rate reading on my wrist at least once.</p>
<p>For much of the last two months, I have been horizontal on my couch or bed, the only apparent position in which my heart rate cannot make me sicker. After the scooter ride left me feeling worse for about 5 weeks, I am still too scared to resume daily walks — not wanting to inadvertantly push too far again.</p>
<p>I’ve also since been diagnosed by a cardiologist with <strong>POTS</strong>, or at least something like it. POTS stands for <strong>Postural Orthostatic Tachychardia Syndrome</strong>, and it’s a common co-morbidity among those of us who haven’t recovered from Covid. POTS is a nervous system dysfunction that makes the body unable to comfortably tolerate being upright. As I had experienced, it typically shows up through elevated heart rate and a complex constellation of potential symptoms. The root cause is unknown and probably heterogeneous, though it commonly starts after viral infections. Like with many other post-viral conditions, there is no medically-approved cure at this point.</p>
</section>
<section id="data" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data">Data</h2>
<p>To meet the diagnostic criteria for POTS, you need to have a heart rate that jumps 30 beats per minute upon standing. You also need to rule out that the increase in heart rate coincides with changes in your blood pressure, such as a drop in blood pressure that could cause elevated heart rate.</p>
<p>I demonstrated to my cardiologist that I met the criteria using a test called the (unfortunately named) <strong>Poor Man’s Tilt Test</strong>. Below are data from four days of heart rate and blood pressure readings I took using a standard blood pressure cuff, first thing in the morning. Looking at the results, it wasn’t unusual for my heart rate to increase by over 40 upon standing. Such an increase is large, since even an increase of 20 is considered <strong>orthostatic intolerance</strong>. Meanwhile, my blood pressure readings were generally stable. So, POTS.</p>
<div class="cell" data-layout-align="center">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://leonidliu.github.io/long_covid_blog/posts/pots-1/index_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="552"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Still, I’d say that I am presenting on the milder-to-moderate side of POTS, at least for now. Far too many people with POTS are fully unable to leave their beds for months at a time, and I’ve heard reports of people whose heart rate can jump to 170 just after standing up.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-im-trying" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-im-trying">What I’m trying</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>At this point, I’m on 2.5mg of ivabradine, twice a day. It’s a drug that slows your heart rate, originally designed for those with heart failure. It can also help people with POTS — often, I’m told, without as many side effects as beta blockers.</p></li>
<li><p>I drink 2-3 liters of water a day to boost blood volume. Once a day, I mix a liter of water with a packet of Triorial, which uses a World Health Organization-approved oral rehydration formula that includes over 2,600 mg of salt per packet to help my body retain hydration.</p></li>
<li><p>Also, I am at the very beginning of trying a particular physical rehabilitation program — a modified version of the <a href="https://www.dysautonomiainternational.org/pdf/CHOP_Modified_Dallas_POTS_Exercise_Program.pdf">CHOP protocol for POTS</a> — designed by a Long Covid POTS patient with for those recovering from similar conditions. The program starts with five minutes of horizontal exercise every other day, with a break after every minute of exercise during which I wait for my heart rate to fall back down. If it doesn’t, then I stop for the day.</p></li>
<li><p>In addition, I am trying to add more ‘exercises’ that I have heard can be helpful in regulating the nervous system: adding cold water exposure to the end of my showers, breathing exercises (e.g., <a href="https://www.stasis.life/">STASIS breathing</a>), and meditation.</p></li>
<li><p>Lastly, I got the Pfizer bivalent booster a few weeks ago. While everyone’s reaction is a little different, particularly for those with Long Covid, some people do report general improvement after getting a vaccine, which is why I consider it a potential POTS intervention.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="how-its-going" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-its-going">How it’s going</h2>
<p>I think it’s still too early to say. Nearly two months after the scooter incident, my body has only barely started to stabilize again. I am so grateful to be experiencing a little more stability right now, but I’ve had enough Long Covid setbacks to know that another significant setback might happen again. If I were to experience another flare-up or “crash,” as some of us call them, I might find myself mostly horizontal for weeks again. Nevertheless, right now I am hopeful that, with my intentional POTS-informed physical rehabilitation program and limited exertion otherwise, I will be able to improve without avoid triggering another flare-up or crash.</p>
</section>
<section id="up-next" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="up-next">Up next</h2>
<p>Next time, I plan to write about my Long Covid journey as it relates to the health of my gut microbiome. I’ll include results from the Ombre commercial gut microbiome test that I took!</p>
</section>
<section id="bonus-my-pots-song" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bonus-my-pots-song">Bonus: My POTS Song</h2>
<p>As friends who’ve stayed with me in these past few months know, <a href="https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;source=web&amp;cd=&amp;cad=rja&amp;uact=8&amp;ved=2ahUKEwjc4tCh-qz7AhXwkIkEHcM7CqMQFnoECC8QAQ&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fopen.spotify.com%2Ftrack%2F6RpEhQK2y0rTZQ5y12xB5x&amp;usg=AOvVaw3Iu2aJ5g4Okvlsvdhgvq7K">Naje’s “Go Lay Down”</a> has been my POTS song. I sometimes belt it when I can’t stand up. It brings me great joy, and I share it in case it might bring a smile to someone else struggling with POTS, too.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <category>POTS</category>
  <guid>https://leonidliu.github.io/long_covid_blog/posts/pots-1/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2022 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://leonidliu.github.io/long_covid_blog/posts/pots-1/scooter.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Welcome!</title>
  <dc:creator>Leo Liu</dc:creator>
  <link>https://leonidliu.github.io/long_covid_blog/posts/welcome/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Hello, and welcome to my blog! My name is Leo, and I’m 30 years old. Since June 23, 2022, I’ve been struggling with Long Covid.</p>
<p>Before my first Covid infection this year, I was a triple-vaccinated, healthy, and happy guy living in Washington, DC. I was doing work I found meaningful, dating as a young gay man, and socially active. Physically, I enjoyed biking, hiking, lifting weights, and often packed my social calendar back-to-back without worry or consequence.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://leonidliu.github.io/long_covid_blog/posts/welcome/welcome-pic.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="An Asian man smiling and wearing a face mask, sitting on a couch with a dog on his lap" width="500"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">A picture of me wearing a face mask, with my friend’s dog Walden</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>But for over four months now, I’ve struggled with a relatively new medical condition that has drastically changed the quality of my life. These days, I’m unable to work full-time, rarely leave my apartment, and can’t easily take care of myself. I rely a lot on my wonderful friends and community for rides, companionship, help around the house, and other forms of regular care. Although my doctors are kind, I often leave medical appointments feeling like they didn’t have much to offer, with the root cause of my condition unidentified and approved treatments potentially still years away.</p>
<p>I’m starting this blog to have a place to chronicle the ups and downs of my journey with Long Covid when I can. I hope it can be a place where I can organize the myriad information I consume about Long Covid and its effects on virtually all organ systems of the body, document the results of mini self-experiments in recovery while navigating a condition with no approved treatments, try to uncover what’s going on in my body, and share about the challenging mental and emotional aspects of living with a medical condition that’s left me quite disabled for now.</p>
<p>Perhaps through the process of writing – organizing, fact-checking, separating evidence from theory, and fact from feeling – I can cultivate a greater sense of patience about the journey I’m on and more fully own the story of my illness. I hope it can help my healing journey along, and maybe even the healing journeys of others suffering from conditions similar to mine.</p>
<p>To those interested in my journey, welcome and thank you for following along! To my fellow long haulers, I’m really happy you’re here – and I believe we will get through this somehow.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <guid>https://leonidliu.github.io/long_covid_blog/posts/welcome/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://leonidliu.github.io/long_covid_blog/posts/welcome/welcome-pic.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
